[Music]
welcome to watch new inry in the 2025
Rel release wave one of business Central
in this release wave we added five new
types of telemetry and then you think
wait a minute the agenda says four
that's because financial reporting got
double up so we got uses and changes to
that we've got troubleshooting client
add-ins way to troubleshoot server side
certificate validations in HP client and
finally a way to discover if you're if
you you you or your customers use a dep
deprecated soap so let's get started
with this um any of these already have
Telemetry samples and of course
documentation so the things I'm showing
you here you can find all of that under
aka.ms slbc telemetry examples and then
you simply navigate to kql queries
example queries and then you find all
the kql um if you want to do this
yourself so um the first type of
telemetry is usage of fin financial
reporting um there are two types of
events both whether a user ran a report
on screen and whether a user ran a
report from the request page now why
would you like to have or use what could
you use this Telemetry for um it might
be that you have auditing needs for your
company so that you need to know who is
actually running a financial report so
so that uh that might be a use case here
um the first financial report run on
screen you can see the event here and um
basically it gives you in which
environments uh it happen and then uh
the context like the report row and
column definitions of that particular
report and uh with everything in
Telemetry we also know who ran the
report if you have set up the user
Telemetry
ID related to this is uh whether the
financial report was run from a request
page and therefore a user achieved a
report as a PDF and you might think why
would you need a special event
with a new ID like this one because you
already have Telemetry for report
rendering that's true but for financial
reporting um it actually makes sense to
also lock the report definitions used so
this not not only um will give you that
one financial report was run but which
one it
was the next class of signal is is about
changes to definitions in financial
reporting and there are three different
types of Def definitions in place in
financial reporting the first one is row
definitions the second one is column
definitions and these two together are
combined in a report definition and for
each of these types of definitions uh
you get like the life cycle so whether
this um definition was created modified
deleted or copied there also even events
for so copy could also be an import um
or an export using a configuration
package so I haven't showed that here
but all of that is of course documented
and in the sample so I'm just going to
show you one example with a row
definition all of these life cycle
events follow the same uh style you can
see again an event ID where it happened
and then which definition was modified
for Road definition you would get the
row definition code for column
definitions you would get the column def
definition code and for report
definitions you would get the report def
definition code um so that's in that's
it for for Telemetry for financial
reporting now if I forgot to mention
that of course the all the life cycle
Telemetry for financial report changes
could be useful if you have auditing
requirements where you need to lock or
maybe even get alerted on anyone
changing a financial report definition
if you then combine this with or with
change lck on the actual definitions you
you both have a way here to be alerted
and you can go back to business Central
and see what actually was changed from
what to
what all right next class of telemetry
is troubleshooting client addins this is
a blind spot or was a blind spot until
now and uh but now you have Telemetry on
this notice that this is locked to the
exceptions table this is a new thing um
so not traces not page views but
exceptions um the the so client add-ins
today can be hard to troubleshoot
because as seen from the business
Central platform or client a client
addin is basically just an embedded
iframe that's it and then whatever
happens in that iframe until now um the
client wouldn't really know about and
you wouldn't know about any errors but
now you do you can see um an exception
happening again in which in where in in
which environment it happened in which
company also from which app in which
object and which addin was uh was
throwing the error and the actual errors
are then in uh in more custom Dimensions
here yeah first of all you can also see
which client type something about the
device but then a lot of information
about the error that happened the
assembly uh the outer message inner
message from javascripts um and all of
this is also packaged in a default sorry
in a details Json structure uh where you
even get things like stack traces um so
so that hopefully that's a way for you
to troubleshoot or even discover if
there are problems with client addins in
environment so uh server side
certificate validation is a new thing
the platform the AL runtime is
performing whenever you call from HTP
client in Al call to an endpoint uh
where the endpoint has a CER a
certificate we will actually validate
that and if that cannot be validated
will throw uh this error um and also to
Telemetry with this new um event ID so
again you can see um where it happened
in which extension in which object and
then some details about the certificate
and also the endpoint that was called
and whether it was a get or post um or
whatever HTTP method was was called and
a failure reason so hopefully this will
allow you to uh to find these types of
errors and then correct them before
users call and say what's
wrong the final um events that we added
here in version 26 or in 2025 wave 1 is
whether a customer or an environment is
calling uh if someone is calling into
the environment with with soap uh with
soap protocol on UI pages that is
exposed or UI Page by Microsoft this is
because these soap web services on UI
PES by Microsoft this has been
deprecated and therefore this will be
kind of stop working in a in a later
release um so if you want to find out if
your environment is vulnerable not
vulnerable but will be affected by this
when it it will actually be turned off
you can go check uh the RT
0053 uh event and if that's the case you
need to work on whoever is calling um
you actually don't know that here you
only know which endpoint they call but
you need to find out uh some integration
is calling this with soap and that needs
to
stop that's it for what's new in
Telemetry as always in anything related
to Telemetry is documented here under
aka.ms slbc Telemetry so um hopefully
these new events will help you
troubleshoot and uh examine your
business Central environment even better
than what was possible until now